I suspect that
أظن أن
every aid worker in Africa
كل عاملة إغاثة في إفريقيا
comes to a time in her career
تصل في مرحلة ما في مسارها المهني
when she wants to take all the money for her project —
حيث تكون لها الرغبة في أن تأخذ كل أموال مشروعها
maybe it's a school or a training program —
--ربما تكون مدرسة أو برنامج تدريب--
pack it in a suitcase,
أن تجمعها في حقيبة،
get on a plane flying over the poorest villages in the country,
وأن تحلق بالطائرة فوق أفقر القرى في البلاد،
and start throwing that money out the window.
وأن ترمي تلك الأموال عبر النافذة.
Because to a veteran aid worker,
لأنه بالنسبة لعاملة إغاثة متمرسة،
the idea of putting cold, hard cash
فإن فكرة وضع الأموال نقدا
into the hands of the poorest people on Earth
في يد أفقر الناس على وجه الأرض
doesn't sound crazy,
لا تبدو فكرة جنونية،
it sounds really satisfying.
بل تبدو فعلا أمرا مُرضِيا.
I had that moment right about the 10-year mark,
عشت هذه اللحظة منذ 10 سنوات خلت،
and luckily, that's also when I learned
ولحسن الحظ، كان ذلك الوقت حني علمت أيضا
that this idea actually exists,
أن هذه الفكرة كانت موجودة،
and it might be just what the aid system needs.
وربما كان هذا ما يحتاجه نظام المساعدات فعلا.
Economists call it an unconditional cash transfer,
يسميها علماء الاقتصاد تحويل الأموال غير المشروط،
and it's exactly that: It's cash given
وهذا يعني تماما: أنها أموال ممنوحة
with no strings attached.
دون أي قيود.
Governments in developing countries
كانت الحكومات في الدولة النامية
have been doing this for decades,
تقوم بهذا لعدة عقود،
and it's only now, with more evidence
لكنه الآن فقط،وبأدلة جديدة
and new technology that it's possible
وبوجود التكنولوجيا الجديدة، تبين أنه من الممكن
to make this a model for delivering aid.
جعل هذا نموذجا لتقديم المساعدات.
It's a pretty simple idea, right?
إنها فكرة بسيطة إلى حد ما، أليس كذلك؟
Well, why did I spend a decade doing other stuff
حسنا، لم قضيت عقدا من الزمن في القيام بأشياء أخرى
for the poor?
من أجل الفقراء؟
Honestly, I believed that I could do more good
بصراحة، كنت أؤمن أنه يمكنني القيام بأشـياء أفضل
with money for the poor
باستعمال المال من أجل الفقراء
I held two assumptions:
كانت لي فرضيتان :
One, that poor people are poor in part
أن الفقراء هم كذلك، لأنهم من جهة
because they're uneducated and
غير متعلمون
don't make good choices;
وأنهم لا يختارون الخيارات الصحيحة؛
two is that we then need people like me
ثانيا،أننا نحتاج إلى أناس مثلي
to figure out what they need and get it to them.
لنفهم ما يحتاجونه وبالتالي نوفره لهم.
It turns out, the evidence says otherwise.
لكنه تبين، أن الأدلة تقول عكس ذلك.
In recent years, researchers have been studying
في السنوات القليلة الماضية، عكف الباحثون على دراسة
what happens when we give poor people cash.
مالذي يمكن أن يحصل إذا أعطينا المال نقدا للناس.
Dozens of studies show across the board
تظهرالعشرات من الدراسات على العديد من الأصعدة
that people use cash transfers
أن الناس يستعملون التحويلات النقدية
to improve their own lives.
لتحسين حياتهم.
Pregnant women in Uruguay buy better food
فالنساء الحوامل في الأوروغواي تشترين غذاء أفضل
and give birth to healthier babies.
لتنجبن أطفالا بصحة أفضل.
Sri Lankan men invest in their businesses.
ويستثمر الرجال في سريلانكا في مجالات أعمالهم.
Researchers who studied our work in Kenya
وجد الباحثون الذين درسوا ماقمنا به في كينيا
found that people invested in a range of assets,
أن الناس قد استثمروا في مجموعة من الأصول،
from livestock to equipment to home improvements,
من المواشي إلى التجهيزات المنزلية،
and they saw increases in income
وقد لاحظوا ارتفاعا في مداخيلهم
from business and farming
من التجارة والزراعة
one year after the cash was sent.
بعد عام من إرسال الأموال لهم.
None of these studies found that people
لم تجد هذه الدراسات أيا من الناس
spend more on drinking or smoking
ممن أنفقوا أموالهم في الشرب أو التدخين
or that people work less.
أو أن الناس قد اشتغلوا بشكل أقل.
In fact, they work more.
على العكس، فقد عملوا بشكل أكبر.
Now, these are all material needs.
حسنا ، كل هذه عبارة عن احتياجات مادية.
In Vietnam, elderly recipients used
في الفيتنام،استخدم المستفيدون المسنون
their cash transfers to pay for coffins.
تحويلات أموالهم لدفع ثمن النعوش.
As someone who wonders if Maslow got it wrong,
بالنسبة لشخص كان يتساءل إن كان ماسلو مخطئا،
I find this choice to prioritize spiritual needs
إلا أنني وجدت أن فكرة تقديم الحاجيات الروحية
deeply humbling.
أمر يدعو إلى التواضع.
I don't know if I would have chosen to give food
لا أدري إن كنت سأختار أن أمنح الطعام
or equipment or coffins,
أو تجهيزات أو نعوشا،
which begs the question:
مما يجعل السؤال التالي ملحا:
How good are we at allocating resources
ما مدى حسن توظيفنا للموارد
on behalf of the poor?
نيابة عن الفقراء؟
Are we worth the cost?
هل ندري ماهي التكلفة؟
Again, we can look at empirical evidence
مرة أخرى، يمكننا أن ننظر إلى الأدلة التجريبية
on what happens when we give people stuff
عما يحصل حين نعطي الناس أشياء
of our choosing.
نحن من اختارها.
One very telling study looked at a program in India
ركزت دراسة عميقة جدا إلى أحد البرامج في الهند
that gives livestock to the so-called ultra-poor,
والتي تمنح مواش لمن يسمون " فائقي الفقر"،
and they found that 30 percent of recipients
فوجدوا أن 30 في المائة من المستفيدين
had turned around and sold the livestock they had been given
نظروا حولهم ثم باعوا الماشية التي منحت لهم
for cash.
من أجل المال.
The real irony is,
السخرية الحقيقية هنا،
for every 100 dollars worth of assets
لكل 100 دولار التي تشكل ثمن الأصل
this program gave someone,
الذي يمنحه هذا البرنامج لمستفيد ما
they spent another 99 dollars to do it.
يتم إنفاق 99 دولار تصله المنحة
What if, instead, we use technology to put cash,
ماذا لو،عوضا عن هذا، استعملنا التكنولوجيا لوضع النقود،
whether from aid agencies or from any one of us
سواء كان الأمرعبر وكالات أو من عند أي منا،
directly into a poor person's hands.
مباشرة في يد إنسان فقير.
Today, three in four Kenyans use mobile money,
اليوم، يستعمل 3 من بين كل 4 كينيين الأموال المحولة عبر الهاتف،
which is basically a bank account that can run
والتي هي بالأساس حساب بنكي يمكن أن يدار
on any cell phone.
على أي هاتف محمول.
A sender can pay a 1.6 percent fee
يدفع المرسل 1.6بالمائة كرسوم
and with the click of a button
وبنقرة على زر واحد
send money directly to a recipient's account
يمكنه أن يرسل الأموال مباشرة إلى حساب المستفيد
with no intermediaries.
بدون أي وسيط.
Like the technologies that are disrupting industries
كما هو الشأن بالنسبة لكل هذه التكنولوجيا التي حركت
in our own lives,
عدة مجالات في حياتنا،
payments technology in poor countries
يمكن لتكنولجيا الدفع في الدول الفقيرة
could disrupt aid.
أن تحرك المساعدات.
It's spreading so quickly that it's possible
فهي تنتشر بسرعة لدرجة أنه من الممكن
to imagine reaching billions
تخيل أنها ستصل للملايير
of the world's poor this way.
في العالم الفقير بهذه الطريقة.
That's what we've started to do at GiveDirectly.
وهذا ما بدأنا القيام به في "GiveDirectly".
We're the first organization
نحن أول منظمة
dedicated to providing cash transfers to the poor.
مهتمة بتوفير تحويلات نقدية للفقراء.
We've sent cash to 35,000 people across rural Kenya
أرسلنا أموالا نقدا إلى 35000 شخص في أنحاء القرى في كينيا
and Uganda
وأوغندا
in one-time payments of 1,000 dollars
على دفعات فردية بقيمة 1000 دولار
per family.
للأسرة الواحدة.
So far, we've looked for the poorest people
لحد الآن،بحثنا عن أفقر الأشخاص
in the poorest villages, and in this part of the world,
في أفقر القرى،وفي هذا الجزء من العالم،
they're the ones living in homes
هم أولئك من يعيشون في منازل
made of mud and thatch,
مبنية من الطين والقش،
not cement and iron.
وليس من الإسمنت و الحديد.
So let's say that's your family.
فلنقل تلك هي أسرتك.
We show up at your door with an Android phone.
نأتي إلى باب بيتك مع هاتف آندرويد.
We'll get your name, take your photo
نأخذ اسمك، ونأخذ صورة لك
and a photo of your hut
وصورة لكوخك
and grab the GPS coordinates.
فنحصل على إحداثيات نظام تحديد المواقع.
That night, we send all the data to the cloud,
في تلك الليلة، نرسل كل البيانات إلى السحابة،
and each piece gets checked
يتم فحص كل قطعة
by an independent team
من طرف فريق مستقل
using, for one example, satellite images.
باستعمال صور قمر اصطناعي مثلا.
Then, we'll come back,
بعد ذلك نعود،
we'll sell you a basic cell phone
فنبيعك جهاز هاتف بسيط
if you don't have one already,
إن لم يكن لك جهاز من قبل،
and a few weeks later,
وبعد أسابيع قليلة،
we send money to it.
نبعث لك المال عبره.
Something that five years ago
منذ 5 سنوات كان هذا الأمر
would have seemed impossible
يبدو مستحيلا
we can now do efficiently
لكننا نقوم به الآن بشكل فعال
and free of corruption.
وبدون أي مشاكل.
The more cash we give to the poor,
كلما أعطينا الفقراء أموالا أكثر،
and the more evidence we have that it works,
وكلما حصلنا على أدلة أن هذا الأمر ناجح،
the more we have to reconsider
كلما أعدنا النظر
everything else we give.
في كل شيء آخر نمنحه.
Today, the logic behind aid is too often,
اليوم، الفكرة وراء المساعدات دائما ماتكون،
well, we do at least some good.
حسنا، على الأقل نقوم ببعض الأشياء الجيدة.
When we're complacent
عندما نكون راضين
with that as our bar,
عن هذا السقف،
when we tell ourselves that giving aid
عندما نقول لأنفسنا أن منح المساعدات
is better than no aid at all,
أفضل من عدمه،
we tend to invest inefficiently,
فإننا نستثمر بشكل غير فعال،
in our own ideas that strike us as innovative,
في أفكارنا التي تبدو غير مبدعة،
on writing reports,
في كتابتنا للتقارير،
on plane tickets and SUVs.
في تذاكر الطيران و سيارات الدفع الرباعي.
What if the logic was,
ماذا لو كانت الفكرة الأساسية هي،
will we do better than cash given directly?
هل كان بإمكاننا أن نقوم بأفضل من منح الأموال مباشرة؟
Organizations would have to prove
سيكون على المنظمات أن يثبتوا
that they're doing more good for the poor
أنهم يقدمون صنيعا للفقراء
than the poor can do for themselves.
أكثر مما يقوم به الفقراء لأنفسهم.
Of course, giving cash won't create public goods
بالتأكيد، لن تخلق النقود المصالح العمومية
like eradicating disease or building strong institutions,
مثل القضاء على مرض أو بناء مؤسسات قوية،
but it could set a higher bar
لكن يمكنها أن تضع سقفا أعلى
for how we help individual families
لكيفية مساعدتنا للعائلات
improve their lives.
على تحسين حياتهم.
I believe in aid.
أنا أؤمن بالمساعدات.
I believe most aid is better than just
أؤمن أن معظم المساعدات هي أفضل من مجرد
throwing money out of a plane.
إلقاء الأموال من الطائرة.
I am also absolutely certain
كما أنني مقتنعة قطعا
that a lot of aid today
أن الكثير من المساعدات اليوم
isn't better than giving directly to the poor.
ليست أفضل من إعطاء المال مباشرة للفقراء.
I hope that one day, it will be.
آمل أن يأتي يوم ما حيث يكون هذا ممكنا.
Thank you.
شكرا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)